<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>trendmicro | Federico Maggi</title>
    <link>/tag/trendmicro/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/trendmicro/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>trendmicro</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2009–2023. All rights are reserved to Federico Maggi or the respective authors. Opinions are my own, and not necessarily reflecting the views of my employer. </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 16:01:50 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu7b980d35cd4a053ebe986874a36746b7_63893_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>trendmicro</title>
      <link>/tag/trendmicro/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radio Killed the Radio Stars: Security Analysis of RF Protocols for Industrial Applications</title>
      <link>/post/ir-security/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 16:01:50 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/ir-security/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After having analyzed the several RF protocols for industrial applications,
distributed by global vendors, we discovered that none of them had
sufficient security features to prevent an attacker from hijacking the
communication and manoeuvre the controlled connected machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Summer 2016 the condo we live in went through some renovation work. We had
construction workers here for the about half a year. This was around the time
when I was getting into software-defined radio (SDR) technology, and had
a spectrum analyzer open all the time on my computer. Just for fun. After
a while I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed some peaks of energy around 434MHz. I didn&amp;rsquo;t pay
attention, until when I saw one of the workers holding what looked like
a rugged remote controller with a tiny antenna. I rushed back in my office and
took a closer look at the spectrum: I could clearly see that the peaks were
showing in perfect sync with the noise of the huge crane swinging over my roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a little chat with the worker and asked him: &amp;ldquo;Is there any safety
mechanism? Like, if I push a button to make the load go down, and someone is
under that load, what happens?&amp;rdquo; In the local dialect, he answered something
that I could roughly translate as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;🤬  if you do that, you must have some serious problems.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounded like the perfect project idea to pitch to my colleagues! So I did.
After some back and forth, brainstorming, and someone in the team having
related ideas, we&amp;rsquo;ve decided to go after this, map the market, reverse engineer
the protocols, look in depth into the embedded systems inside these remotes,
and perform an all-around security analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here we are. After a long break in the middle, hard research work, and
a challenging disclosure process, I&amp;rsquo;m very happy to share the results of what
my colleagues in Trend Micro Research and I have produced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the renovation work is done and we&amp;rsquo;re enjoying a shiny new stone
paver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;condo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;End of the renovation work.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;radio-frequency-technology&#34;&gt;Radio-frequency Technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sub-gigaherz radio-frequency (RF) protocols are widely adopted for both
consumer and &lt;strong&gt;industrial applications&lt;/strong&gt;. From simple garage-door openers to
remote controllers that manoeuvre huge mining drillers or overhead cranes that
can lift tons of loads. So, way beyond construction cranes. These RF protocols
operate in the ISM bands (e.g., 433, 868, 915 MHz, depending on the region),
have a &lt;strong&gt;range up to several hundreds meters&lt;/strong&gt;, can easily go through
obstacles, are very low priced, and are very flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;industrial-rf-remote-control-systems&#34;&gt;Industrial RF Remote Control Systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These industrial remote-control systems usually comprise a receiver (RX) with
a few relay switches (e.g., to power up the controlled motor or other
electrical loads), and a transmitter (TX) that looks like a rugged remote
controller with buttons. Both RX and TX have an &lt;strong&gt;embedded digital radio chip&lt;/strong&gt;
and a micro-controller that implements the actual application-level protocol
(e.g., structure of messages, CRCs, pairing, addressing). Each transmitted
message carries a distinct &lt;strong&gt;command&lt;/strong&gt; that the RX actuates, usually by
triggering the relay switches in a given, configurable way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;ir-system.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Industrial Radio Remote Control System in a Nutshell&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;security-angle&#34;&gt;Security Angle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the simplicity of these systems, &lt;strong&gt;there is no standardization&lt;/strong&gt; in the
application-level protocol, nor security best practices that go beyond the use
of rolling-code to avoid replay attacks (in the best case).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having analyzed the systems produced by several global vendors, in our
research we discovered that none of the implementations had any robust security
features (not even rolling codes) that would prevent an attacker from hijacking
the communication and take control of the heavy industrial machines connected
to the RX unit. After having responsibly disclosed our findings through 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zerodayinitiative.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Trend
Micro&amp;rsquo;s ZDI&lt;/a&gt; (
&lt;a href=&#34;/advisories/&#34;&gt;10 advisories and 3 ICS-CERT
alerts&lt;/a&gt;, some of which resulted in security firmware updates), we&amp;rsquo;ve drawn
a list of recommendations for end users, system integrators, and vendors, to
ensure that current-generation systems get properly secured, and that
next-generation systems will be secure by design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;details-nope&#34;&gt;Details? Nope!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been the hard part. Digging into custom protocols and figuring out
all the bits that travel on the SPI bus (to make sure that we&amp;rsquo;re looking
at the right data on the RX side) was challenging, yet a lot, lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, this blog post won&amp;rsquo;t go into the details. There&amp;rsquo;s the white paper (below)
for that! Plus 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trendmicro.com/vinfo/us/security/news/vulnerabilities-and-exploits/attacks-against-industrial-machines-via-vulnerable-radio-remote-controllers-security-analysis-and-recommendations&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this interactive page with demo videos&lt;/a&gt;, and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trendmicro.com/trendlabs-security-intelligence/demonstrating-command-injection-and-e-stop-abuse-against-industrial-radio-remote-controllers/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this blog post that describes a little RF dongle we&amp;rsquo;ve built for this research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve presented this research at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://direction.trendmicro.com/sess/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Direction Tokyo last
November&lt;/a&gt; (by the way, my first
encounter with the Japanese culture was stellar!), my colleague

&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/miaoski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Philippe&lt;/a&gt; has presented 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hitcon.org/2018/pacific/downloads/1213-R1/1610-1650.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;it at HITCON
pacific&lt;/a&gt;
focusing on the firmware reverse-engineering, and my colleagues

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/jonathan-andersson-b516b9/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jonathan&lt;/a&gt;
(
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.engadget.com/2016/10/28/icarus-hijack-dmsx-drones/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
Jonathan) and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sjhilt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stephen&lt;/a&gt; have just presented the
white paper today at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://s4xevents.com/sessions/the-industrial-radio-project/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the S4
conference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;media&#34;&gt;Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not attempting to keep track of the media activity around this research, sorry!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://monoist.atmarkit.co.jp/mn/articles/1811/19/news054.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;あなたの機械、安易につなげて大丈夫？　リスクと攻撃手法を知る&lt;/a&gt;, Nov 19th, 2018&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itmedia.co.jp/news/articles/1811/29/news027.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;クレーンを不正に遠隔操作、10年前より「攻撃しやすい」？　専門家が注意喚起&lt;/a&gt;, Nov 29th, 2018&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scott Shuey, Gulf News, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gulfnews.com/technology/the-next-cyber-threat-wont-be-over-the-internet-its-on-the-radio-1.61093289&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The next cyber threat won’t be over the internet, it’s on the radio&lt;/a&gt; (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://gulfnews.newspaperdirect.com/epaper/viewer.aspx?issue=11252019010400000000001001&amp;amp;page=18&amp;amp;article=47eb5960-bdd2-487e-a806-eca02e63fc0e&amp;amp;key=KkfY%2BCKWAUSFjN6c%2Fj%2Bzmg%3D%3D&amp;amp;feed=rss&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;print version&lt;/a&gt;). Jan 5th, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thomas Brewster, Forbes, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/thomasbrewster/2019/01/15/exclusive-watch-hackers-take-control-of-giant-construction-cranes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Watch Hackers Take Control Of Giant Construction Cranes&lt;/a&gt;. Jan 15th, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sean Lyngaas, CyberScoop, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cyberscoop.com/crane-hack-radio-frequency-trend-micro-s4x19/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Look to the sky: How hackers could control cranes by abusing radio frequencies&lt;/a&gt;, Jan 15th, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

  
  

  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    

  
  &lt;span&gt;Federico Maggi&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Marco Balduzzi&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Jonathan Andersson&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Philippe Lin&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Stephen Hilt&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Akira Urano&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Rainer Vosseler&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  (2019).
  &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/maggi_industrialradios_2019/&#34;&gt;A Security Evaluation of Industrial Radio Remote Controllers&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on Detection of Intrusions and Malware, and Vulnerability Assessment (DIMVA)&lt;/em&gt;.
  
  &lt;p&gt;








  



&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;/publication/maggi_industrialradios_2019/maggi_industrialradios_2019.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  PDF
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;button type=&#34;button&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/publication/maggi_industrialradios_2019/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/button&gt;














&lt;/p&gt;

  
  
&lt;/div&gt;



  &lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

  
  

  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    

  
  &lt;span&gt;Jonathan Andersson&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Marco Balduzzi&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Stephen Hilt&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Philippe Lin&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Federico Maggi&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Akira Urano&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Rainer Vosseler&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  (2019).
  &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/andersson_industrialradioswp_tr_2019/&#34;&gt;A Security Analysis of Radio Remote Controllers for Industrial Applications&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;em&gt;Trend Micro Research&lt;/em&gt;.
  
  &lt;p&gt;








  



&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;/publication/andersson_industrialradioswp_tr_2019/andersson_industrialradioswp_tr_2019.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  PDF
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;button type=&#34;button&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/publication/andersson_industrialradioswp_tr_2019/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/button&gt;














&lt;/p&gt;

  
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Scale Analysis of Defaced Web Pages</title>
      <link>/post/large-scale-deface-page-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2018 15:21:19 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/large-scale-deface-page-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given the multiple releases around this topic and project, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to
put together a summary. So far, there is: a tool, a white paper, an
academic paper, and (spoiler alert) another white paper coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’d be surprised (I was!) how much the modus operandi and the motivation
behind web defacement have evolved and mutated over the past ~20 years. From
attackers interested in pointing their finger to vulnerable websites, to modern
actors taking strong positions on real-world conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;i/real-world-timeline.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Timeline of real world events for which we have found evidence in web-deface pages.&#34; title=&#34;Timeline of Real World Events&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we know what we know about this phenomenon? Let&amp;rsquo;s take a look!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tool&#34;&gt;The Tool&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/toolswatch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Black Hat US Arsenal&lt;/a&gt; my
colleagues and I released 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/trendmicro/defplorex&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;part of the source code of
DefPloreX&lt;/a&gt;, the tool-chain that we use
to explore million of web-deface pages. DefPloreX is pretty flexible and, in
principle, it could be used to process any web page, for instance those planted
as a result of an attack, or to &amp;ldquo;cluster&amp;rdquo; together web pages of underground web
sites, and any other e-crime forensics task that requires to &amp;ldquo;make sense&amp;rdquo; out
of a large dataset of web pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/trendmicro/defplorex/blob/master/i/dpx-overall.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;DefPloreX workflow&#34; title=&#34;DefPloreX workflow&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DefPloreX ingests plain and flat tabular files (e.g., CSV files) containing
metadata records of web incidents under analysis (e.g., URLs), renders them and
obtains a copy of their resources with headless browsers (we tried basically
all of them, but then we settled with Chrome via

&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/GoogleChrome/puppeteer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Puppeteer&lt;/a&gt;), extracts numerical
features, and stores the resulting data to an Elastic index. We&amp;rsquo;ve designed any
task to be distributed by default, using Celery to coordinate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of the Elastic back-end, I&amp;rsquo;ve cooked up a ReactJS-based web-app (which
as of now is not part of the open-source release, mainly because the code is
&lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; messy) to interactively explore, query, and dig into the data. This
allows an analyst to easily investigate on campaigns, for example in
discovering websites targeted by the same campaign or attributing one or more
actors to the same hacking group. All of this without sacrificing the
interactivity aspect of the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/trendmicro/defplorex/blob/master/i/dpx-clusters-viz.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;DefPloreX web app main screen&#34; title=&#34;DefPloreX web app main screen&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to see the web app in action, you can take yourself a 14 minutes coffee or tea break while watching this demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DILbSXYpiMU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;distributed-data-processing&#34;&gt;Distributed Data Processing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, to take full advantage of Elastic&amp;rsquo;s distributed data-processing
functionality, you need to resort to

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/elasticsearch/reference/current/modules-scripting.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;scripting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although scripting is quite powerful and handy for small data-manipulation
tasks, it&amp;rsquo;s a bit cumbersome to deploy and handle requires; and, in addition,
it requires full access to the Elastic&amp;rsquo;s client nodes. For example, if you need
to process all the documents in an Elastic index (e.g., to enrich them by
computing additional fields), you will have to choose one of the scripting
languages supported by Elastic, write a script, deploy it and run it. Needless
to say, your script will run within the context of the ES runtime, with all the
limitations that this implies. For example, should you need to use Python,
you&amp;rsquo;re forced to use the Jython Java implementation of Python, which is not the
same as pure Python. For instance, some of the libraries that you may want to
use may not be supported, and so on. In other words, we don&amp;rsquo;t want to depend on
the Elastic&amp;rsquo;s scripting subsystem in our work :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, we take a more &amp;ldquo;detached&amp;rdquo; approach. We decouple the data-processing
part, making it independent from the Elastic runtime and architecture, and rely
on ES exclusively as a data back-end to store, retrieve and modify JSON
documents. The coordination of the distributed computation is delegated to
a well-known and widely used distributed task queue:

&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.celeryproject.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Celery&lt;/a&gt;. The friendliness of Celery is
astonishing: from the programmer&amp;rsquo;s perspective, all it requires is to write
your data-processing code by means of a function, and Celery will take care of
offloading the (expensive and long-running) computation to one of the available
workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/trendmicro/defplorex/blob/master/i/dpx-celery.png?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;DefPloreX distributed data processing via Celery&#34; title=&#34;DefPloreX distributed data processing via Celery&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you need to visit a web page with an automated headless
browser, all you need to do is to wrap your code into a function, let&amp;rsquo;s say
&lt;code&gt;visit_page&lt;/code&gt;, and decorate it with &lt;code&gt;@app.task&lt;/code&gt; to inform Celery that this is
a task:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;@app.task
def visit_page(url):
    result = long_running_process(url)

    return result
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on in your code, all you need to do is to call the function (almost) as
you would normally do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;visit_page.delay(url)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;.delay()&lt;/code&gt; function indicates that the function call will not execute
immediately, but instead will be &amp;ldquo;pushed&amp;rdquo; into a task list, from which an
available worker will pull it and do the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the task list, you can launch as many workers as you need,
by simply keeping the Celery daemon active:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;$ celery worker --autoscale=6,64
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming a 64-core machine, this command spawns 6 concurrent processes, up to
64 when more workload comes in. And of course you can add as many workers as
needed, from a single computer with a few tenths of cores, to a full rack
distributed across the globe. In our deployment, we have 5 machines, with
a total of 128 cores. With these modest resources, we were able to visit the
entire collection of over 13 million web pages in a week. Adding more cores
would have made the analysis even faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;document-transformations&#34;&gt;Document Transformations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this moment on, we have a solid foundation to efficiently transform JSON
documents stored in the Elastic index. Therefore, we &amp;ldquo;encode&amp;rdquo; any operation
that we need to perform in DefPloreX by means of a few lines of Python code. For
example, we often need to &amp;ldquo;tag&amp;rdquo; JSON documents to mark those that have been
processed. To this end, as exemplified in this repository, we use the
&lt;code&gt;TagTransformer&lt;/code&gt; transformation. As any other transform, this function receives one JSON
document and returns the newly added fields, or the modified fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class TagTransformer(Transformer):
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    Example transform to append tag to a record.
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    _name = &#39;tag&#39;                   # unique name

    def __call__(self, doc, *args, **kwargs):
        doc = super(TagTransformer, self).__call__(
                doc, *args, **kwargs)

        tag = kwargs.get(&#39;tag&#39;)     # tag that we want to apply to the JSON

        if not tag:
            log.debug(&#39;No tags supplied, skipping&#39;)
            return []

        tags = doc.get(&#39;tags&#39;, [])  # get the &#39;tags&#39; field from the existing JSON doc

        if tags:
            log.debug(&#39;Found tags: %s&#39;, tags)

        tags.append(tag)            # append the new tag
        tags = list(set(tags))      # remove duplicates

        log.debug(&#39;Updated tags: %s&#39;, tags)

        return dict(tags=tags)      # return the enriched JSON
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The output of this transformation is automatically handled by our Elastic
wrapper (see &lt;code&gt;backend.elastic.ESStorer&lt;/code&gt;) and the
&lt;code&gt;transformer.Pipeline&lt;/code&gt; class, which merges the new (partial) document with the
original one and saves it into the ES index. Actually, this is
performed in bulk: that is, every worker consumes and processes a given amount
of documents at each round (default is 1000). To summarize: given a query, we
enqueue all the IDs of the documents that match that query. The queue consumers
will pull 1000 IDs at a time, query Elastic for the respective documents,
transform them, and push them back on Elastic as update operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other transformations that we have implemented (briefly explained in
the following) include for example visiting the web pages with an automated,
headless browser, extracting information from the visited web pages,
calculating numerical features, and so on. Every task is expressed by means of
a subclass of &lt;code&gt;Transformer&lt;/code&gt;, which takes as input a document, and returns the
enriched or modified fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-white-paper&#34;&gt;The White Paper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the help of our great colleagues at TrendLabs, we prepared a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trendmicro.com/vinfo/us/security/news/cyber-attacks/web-defacements-exploring-the-methods-of-hacktivists&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;white
paper&lt;/a&gt;
that focuses on the major campaigns, and how DefPloreX helped explore them. In
particular, we look at 7 campaigns that have affected Israel, France,
India, Syria, Kosovo, and countries surrounding the South China Sea. We dig
into specific conflicts in those areas and the defacements that happened in the
aftermath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;i/wp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A Deep Dive into Defacement: How Geopolitical Events Trigger Web Attacks&#34; title=&#34;A Deep Dive into Defacement: How Geopolitical Events Trigger Web Attacks&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To &lt;del&gt;feed our curiosity and&lt;/del&gt;~ help CERTs understand better the origin of these
attacks and modus-operandi of the groups, we also look how they are organized
(some are formed across continents, and some are a loose collection of local
hackers), as well as how their recruitment tools and the methods adopt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-devil-answer-is-in-the-details&#34;&gt;The &lt;del&gt;Devil&lt;/del&gt; Answer is in the Details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering how exactly the data-mining workflow works, what
features we use, what clustering algorithm and so on. For the impatient, here&amp;rsquo;s a quick overview of the data that we process and the features that we extract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;i/data.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Metadata and raw content available in our dataset, along with a description of the trustworthiness of each attribute.&#34; title=&#34;Metadata and raw content available in our dataset, along with a description of the trustworthiness of each attribute.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;i/features.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Clustering features that we extract from each deface page.&#34; title=&#34;Clustering features that we extract from each deface page.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, now, how do we use these features for clustering?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very thankful to Roberto Perdisci for the valuable insights that he
provided on this work about the machine-learning and data-mining part. What I&amp;rsquo;m
most thankful about, however, is the suggestion to use BIRCH, which I didn&amp;rsquo;t
know before. I think this figure speaks by itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;i/dbscan-vs-birch.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;BIRCH vs. DBSCAN.&#34; title=&#34;BIRCH vs. DBSCAN.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressive, huh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

  
  

  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    

  
  &lt;span&gt;Federico Maggi&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Marco Balduzzi&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Ryan Flores&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Lion Gu&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Vincenzo Ciancaglini&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  (2018).
  &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/maggi_defplorex_2018/&#34;&gt;Investigating Web Defacement Campaigns at Large&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 2018 on Asia Conference on Computer and Communications Security&lt;/em&gt;.
  
  &lt;p&gt;








  



&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;/publication/maggi_defplorex_2018/maggi_defplorex_2018.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  PDF
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;button type=&#34;button&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/publication/maggi_defplorex_2018/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/button&gt;














&lt;/p&gt;

  
  
&lt;/div&gt;



  &lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

  
  

  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    

  
  &lt;span&gt;Marco Balduzzi&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Federico Maggi&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Vincenzo Ciancaglini&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Ryan Flores&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Lion Gu&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  (2017).
  &lt;a href=&#34;/talk/balduzzi_defplorexbhus_talk_2017/&#34;&gt;DefPloreX: A Machine Learning Toolkit for Large-scale e-Crime Forensics&lt;/a&gt;.
  
  &lt;p&gt;








  



&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;/talk/balduzzi_defplorexbhus_talk_2017/balduzzi_defplorexbhus_talk_2017.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  PDF
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;button type=&#34;button&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/talk/balduzzi_defplorexbhus_talk_2017/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/button&gt;











  
  
    
  
&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DILbSXYpiMU&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  Video
&lt;/a&gt;




&lt;/p&gt;

  
  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dnsmasq and CVE-2017-1449*: A Reality Check and Remediation Practices</title>
      <link>/post/dnsmasq/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2017 15:09:24 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/dnsmasq/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many vulnerabilities in one shot, yet several pre-conditions for a target to
be actually exploitable. Here&amp;rsquo;s simple flowchart to check whether your
Dnsmasq deployments are vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thekelleys.org.uk/dnsmasq/doc.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dnsmasq&lt;/a&gt; is the de-facto tool
to implement DNS and DHCP services in small servers and embedded devices. Being
Dnsmasq user, when 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://security.googleblog.com/2017/10/behind-masq-yet-more-dns-and-dhcp.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Security researchers disclosed the CVE-2017-14491 to
14496
series&lt;/a&gt;,
I quickly checked whether my installation was vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turned out that, despite I found a vast amount of devices running a vulnerable
version of Dnsmasq, the chain of pre-conditions for these vulnerabilities to be
exploitable are not super trivial. So I decided to write them down in
a flowchart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.trendmicro.com/trendlabs-security-intelligence/dnsmasq-reality-check-remediation-practices/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the full blog post here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From a Bit-flipping to a Vulnerability in the CAN Standard</title>
      <link>/post/candos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2017 12:49:04 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/candos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CAN-based protocols are vulnerable to bit-flipping attacks at the link layer.
In this collaborative research, Politecnico di Milano&amp;rsquo;s

&lt;a href=&#34;https://necst.it&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NECSTLab&lt;/a&gt; and Trend Micro&amp;rsquo;s FTR analyze the protocol in
depth and demonstrate the vulnerability on a real car, with PoC and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project started somewhere between 2015 and 2016. Back then, I was an
Assistant Professor at Politecnico di Milano. Together with my colleague

&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/raistolo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stefano&lt;/a&gt;, I was advising this bright Master
student, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/andreapalanca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Andrea Palanca&lt;/a&gt;, who was
basically &amp;ldquo;breathing cars,&amp;rdquo; and really passionate about car hacking. So it made
a lot of sense to introduce him to 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.evenchick.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Eric Evencick&lt;/a&gt;,
who then became part of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric had this idea of looking at the link layer of the CAN protocol, given the
numerous frame-injection attacks popping up here and there. However, we&amp;rsquo;ve
thought, injecting frame in the CAN bus is pretty noisy, and also quite easy to
detect with some smart monitoring. Indeed, knowing the network architecture and
ECUs attached to it (and, let&amp;rsquo;s be honest, they don&amp;rsquo;t change that often even in
a connected car), it&amp;rsquo;s fairly easy to figure out if a frame is out of order, or
simply unexpected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrea then started to dig into the CAN bus standard, using his own car as
a playground, and quickly came up with a prototype testbed CAN deployment in
the lab, on which he started to explore the effect of flipping &amp;ldquo;the right bit
at the right time&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, enough high-level talking! It&amp;rsquo;s time to take a look at the actual
content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gimme-da-video&#34;&gt;Gimme da Video!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following short video you can see me presenting the work to an academic
audience. True fact: I&amp;rsquo;ve recorded this while preparing my talk for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://itsec.cs.uni-bonn.de/dimva2017/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DIMVA
2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/oajtDFw_t3Q&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;additional-material&#34;&gt;Additional Material&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re curious to know more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for an intermediate-level description, you can read our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trendmicro.com/trendlabs-security-intelligence/connected-car-hack/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for a more in-depth piece, head over to the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://documents.trendmicro.com/assets/A-Vulnerability-in-Modern-Automotive-Standards-and-How-We-Exploited-It.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;technical brief (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you&amp;rsquo;re using CAN in your products, you might be interested in our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ics-cert.us-cert.gov/alerts/ICS-ALERT-17-209-01&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;disclosure through the ICS-CERT (ICS-ALERT-17-209-01)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

  
  

  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    

  
  &lt;span&gt;Andrea Palanca&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Eric Evenchick&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Federico Maggi&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Stefano Zanero&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  (2017).
  &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/palanca_candos_2017/&#34;&gt;A Stealth, Selective, Link-Layer Denial-of-Service Attack Against Automotive Networks&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Detection of Intrusions and Malware, and Vulnerability Assessment (DIMVA)&lt;/em&gt;.
  
  &lt;p&gt;








  



&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;/publication/palanca_candos_2017/palanca_candos_2017.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  PDF
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;button type=&#34;button&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/publication/palanca_candos_2017/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/button&gt;














&lt;/p&gt;

  
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Role of Industrial Routers in Keeping the Future Factory Secure</title>
      <link>/post/industrial-routers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2017 12:39:46 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/industrial-routers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Industrial routers play a very crucial role: a single vulnerability can grant
the attacker access to an entire network of critical machines. In this
research, I&amp;rsquo;ve looked at how easy it is for a hypothetical attacker to find
and enumerate industrial routers, and the security posture of their vendors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Industrial routers aren&amp;rsquo;t just regular routers in a rugged case. They are the
gateway to networks of &lt;em&gt;machines&lt;/em&gt;, which usually end up interacting with the
physical world. Think about connected vehicles, factories, robots, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While working on a remote access box (another name for &amp;ldquo;industrial router&amp;rdquo;),
during our 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://robosec.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;industrial robots research&lt;/a&gt;, we noticed that
the web-admin panel had an authentication-bypass vulnerability. Upon reporting
the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://websupport.ewon.biz/support/news/support/ewon-security-enhancement-fw-112s2-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;vulnerability to the vendor, which patched it right
away&lt;/a&gt;,
we&amp;rsquo;ve wondered: are there other vendors? What&amp;rsquo;s the state of security in this
area?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After going through the &amp;ldquo;Switches Get Stitches&amp;rdquo; talks (
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/44Con/switches-getstitches&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;44CON 2014&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://media.ccc.de/v/31c3_-_6196_-_en_-_saal_1_-_201412281130_-_switches_get_stitches_-_eireann_leverett&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;31C3 2014&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=urjKkQaspHQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Black Hat US 2015&lt;/a&gt;),
we had some bad feelings about industrial routers too, so we&amp;rsquo;ve started to
collect technical resources like manuals and firmware update files, and crafted
Shodan and Censys search strings to see how many of these routers were directly
exposed to a casual attacker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing that we&amp;rsquo;ve noticed was the abundance of technical information
freely available to the public. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong: I&amp;rsquo;m not advocating in favor
of &amp;ldquo;security through obscurity&amp;rdquo; nor &amp;ldquo;closed source&amp;rdquo;. Once I believe in
openness, I also believe that critical targets like industrial routers (which
are put in front of supposedly critical machinery), shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; easy
for a casual attacker to discover. Ironically, marketing brochures required
a registration, whereas firmware and technical manuals were directly indexed by
search engines and publicly accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the security posture of some vendors, we&amp;rsquo;ve decided to take a broad look
at all of them, both from a reconnaissance and vulnerability viewpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re curious, head over to the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trendmicro.com/trendlabs-security-intelligence/compromising-industrial-robots/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;full article&lt;/a&gt; on TrendLab&amp;rsquo;s Security Intelligence Blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What we Know About Eyepyramid</title>
      <link>/post/eyepyramid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 12:16:11 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/eyepyramid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The day before the EyePyramid case exploded, I received a confidential email
with a PDF. It was the scanned copy of the court order for the law enforcement
to proceed and arrest the Occhionero brothers. In a few minutes, I noticed that
this leaked document was also circulating on various private mailing lists and
chat groups I&amp;rsquo;m part of. At some point, I received a non-redacted copy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;responsive-wrap&#34;&gt;
	&lt;object data=&#34;ordinanza-occhionero.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; style=&#34;margin: 0 auto;height: 100vh;width: 100%;&#34;&gt;
		&lt;embed src=&#34;ordinanza-occhionero.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf &#34;style=&#34;margin: 0 auto;height: 100vh;width: 100%;&#34;&gt;
			&lt;em&gt;It seems that your browser cannot display the PDF file; Please use this &lt;a href=&#34;ordinanza-occhionero.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;link&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt;
			instead. Thanks!&lt;/em&gt;
	&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I typically do not work on e-crime investigation cases, but while reading the
court order I felt that something was not completely right. Moreover, the case
was in Italy, my home country, which motivated me to look at it. Then, some
colleagues from Trend Micro Italy contacted me with questions coming from our
clients (for which, back then, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t answer yet). So, at the end of the
day I decided to dive in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;puzzling-facts-in-the-court-order&#34;&gt;Puzzling Facts in the Court Order&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I skimmed through the court order and was surprised by the vast amount of
technical evidence provided to support the accusations. Email addresses (in
clear or easy to guess when redacted), IP addresses, domain names. So detailed
that I could basically write a Yara rule to hunt for malware samples, without
even looking at a single binary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, the part that puzzled me most. The author of the malware used
a licensed software library and allegedly &lt;em&gt;purchased the license under the name
of Giulio Occhionero&lt;/em&gt; (one of the two brothers). It&amp;rsquo;s like, leaving your name
on the crime scene!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;almost-live-reversing&#34;&gt;(Almost) Live Reversing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After getting my hands on some samples (yes, with Yara hunting rules based on
the court order), things escalated quickly, and found myself looking at nearly
250 samples. With the help of my fine colleagues, we&amp;rsquo;ve drawn rough, big
picture of the whole scheme and started to find confirmatory evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a few hours, people on Twitter and other social networks started to follow
the case closely, comment on it, give their own views. Given some confusion,
I felt the urge to publish a list of &amp;ldquo;cold, simple, yet true&amp;rdquo; technical facts.
So I&amp;rsquo;ve spun up a GitHub Gist (now deleted), which then evolved in a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/eyepyramid/eyepyramid&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;full
repository&lt;/a&gt; (now not updated
anymore), and finally 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@phretor/cosa-sappiamo-su-eyepyramid-61b5b88c63b8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a post on Medium (in
Italian)&lt;/a&gt;.
Results were popping up rapidly, so I found myself unable to keep up with the
pace, and decided to stop &amp;ldquo;live reversing&amp;rdquo; the samples, set aside some time and
prepare two comprehensive posts for TrendLab&amp;rsquo;s Intelligence Blog, which my
employer was very happy to release in no time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jan 18, 2017 - 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trendmicro.com/trendlabs-security-intelligence/uncovering-inner-workings-eyepyramid/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Uncovering the Inner Workings of EyePyramid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jan 11, 2017 - 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trendmicro.com/trendlabs-security-intelligence/eye-storm-look-eyepyramid-malware-supposedly-used-high-profile-hacks-italy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Eye of the Storm: A Look at EyePyramid, the Malware Supposedly Used in High-Profile Hacks in Italy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary-of-the-case&#34;&gt;Summary of the Case&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, the original source code had gone through only very mild
modifications (e.g., not all variants are able to exfiltrate Skype
conversations, C&amp;amp;C and dropzones, compiler version, and protection mechanisms).
On the other hand, the computer(s) used to build the various versions over the
years seemed to be in line with the evolution of Microsoft developer tools
(based on the progression of the compiler version) and software-protection
tools (as seen on the recent substitution of Skater plus Dotfuscator with the
more powerful ConfuserEx). This indicates that the actors behind this operation
knew what they were doing. Of course, this was (and still) far from being an advanced
or targeted piece of malware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, the origins of EyePyramid’s malware and its attribution remain
a mystery. While the license key registered to Giulio Occhionero’s name can be
considered as strong evidence, it is unclear why a malware author would bother
using (simple yet not so trivial) mechanisms to cover their traces (e.g.,
obfuscation, packing, encryption, disabling security tools), and then
mistakenly embed the license key under his name in all of the main variants.
Moreover, an analysis of the domain-to-IP historical data of the domain names
listed in the court order reveals domains named &lt;code&gt;occhionero.com&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;occhionero.info&lt;/code&gt;, which is again another oddity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;latest-update-just-another-oddity&#34;&gt;Latest Update (Just Another Oddity)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I received an unexpected email message from someone I&amp;rsquo;ve never heard before.
Despite the author of this email is not known in the cyber security community
(he presented himself as a PhD Student in medicine at Stanford), he took the
time (and money) to verify every single email address written in my analysis
and in the court order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using LeakedSource (now taken down) he had found that one of the compromised
email addresses (&lt;code&gt;lu_1974[@]hotmail.com&lt;/code&gt;, which is linked to EyePyramid) was
used to register on various dating sites. LeakedSource was borderline websites
that hosted stolen information, including usernames and
passwords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“this is probably just a coincidence”&lt;/em&gt; he said but &lt;em&gt;“Giulio also used his
&lt;code&gt;@westlands.com&lt;/code&gt; address to register to the same dating sites.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, I&amp;rsquo;ve replied back, thanking him for his work. Then I&amp;rsquo;ve asked him why
a Stanford PhD Student in medicine was so interested in such “niche” case
(unfolded from the other side of the world), and how he knew that Giulio
Occhionero had used his &lt;code&gt;@westlands.com&lt;/code&gt; address to register to the same dating
sites, because I could not find any evidence about it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve never gotten a reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;media&#34;&gt;Media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After getting in touch with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/carolafrediani&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Carola
Frediani&lt;/a&gt;, who did a very good job
consolidating all the facts for La Stampa (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lastampa.it/2017/01/12/italia/cronache/tutti-i-dettagli-e-i-misteri-di-eyepyramid-S3vOtTe6smhbJbBlrogpcJ/pagina.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tutti i dettagli e i misteri di
EyePyramid&lt;/a&gt;),
I happily joined the hacker&amp;rsquo;s corner at the International Journalism Festival
2017 in Perugia, a few months later, in a panel moderated by Carola. Here&amp;rsquo;s
the recording of the panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/icgJavQqICM&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobile (Android) Ransomware</title>
      <link>/post/mobile-ransomware/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 01:32:15 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/mobile-ransomware/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve started this project while advising a Master student who was interested
in machine learning. As I&amp;rsquo;ve been using machine learning since around 2006, I
was immediately hooked by the idea of using it to determine whether an
Android app was trying to lock the target device as part of a ransomware
scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three core characteristics that are unavoidable for any ransomware
scheme, which can be all boiled down to the &amp;ldquo;business&amp;rdquo; need of &amp;ldquo;being noisy&amp;rdquo;
and evident. It&amp;rsquo;s true right? For the first time we see malware that is no
longer trying to hide. Instead, it needs to loudly announce its presence to the
victim, in order for the business model to work. If the victim is not aware of
what is happening and is not effectively guided to the payment screen, the
infection is useless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, any ransomware needs to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;encrypt or lock access to important data,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;announce its presence to the user and,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;guide them through the payment options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These three features &lt;strong&gt;have to be implemented&lt;/strong&gt; by a ransomware sample, and
thus have to be visible somehow in the code. Around this key observation,
together with the evil genius 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.andronio.me/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nicolò Andronio&lt;/a&gt; (the
aforementioned Master student) and my partner-in-crime

&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/raistolo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stefano&lt;/a&gt;, we devised and open-sourced

&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/necst/heldroid&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HelDroid&lt;/a&gt;, a fully automatic APK analyzer
that, using static flow analysis, detects whether an app contains evidence of
ransomware behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this summer I&amp;rsquo;ve joined 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trendmicro.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Trend Micro&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s
research team, and immediately got my hands onto MARS, its 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mars.trendmicro.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mobile App
Reputation Service&lt;/a&gt;, which allowed me to build
a good retrospective view of how Android ransomware have evolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work granted me a speaking slot at the Black Hat Europe Briefings, where
I had the opportunity to present the results to a room packed with attendees.
Was a great experience!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re curious, you can read a summarized version of the research in these
two blog posts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trendmicro.com/trendlabs-security-intelligence/mobile-ransomware-pocket-sized-badness/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mobile Ransomware: Pocket-Sized Badness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.trendmicro.com/trendlabs-security-intelligence/mobile-ransomware-protect/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mobile Ransomware: How to Protect Against It&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20180216035340/http://ransom.mobi/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;web service (archived)&lt;/a&gt; in case you want to check it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

  
  

  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    

  
  &lt;span&gt;Chenghyu Zheng&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Nicola Della Rocca&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Niccolò Andronio&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Stefano Zanero&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Maggi Federico&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  (2016).
  &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/zheng_greateatlon_2016/&#34;&gt;GreatEatlon: Fast, Static Detection of Mobile Ransomware&lt;/a&gt;.
  
  &lt;p&gt;








  



&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;/publication/zheng_greateatlon_2016/zheng_greateatlon_2016.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  PDF
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;button type=&#34;button&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/publication/zheng_greateatlon_2016/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/button&gt;














&lt;/p&gt;

  
  
&lt;/div&gt;



  &lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

  
  

  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    

  
  &lt;span&gt;Niccolò Andronio&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Stefano Zanero&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span&gt;Federico Maggi&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  (2015).
  &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/andronio_heldroid_2015/&#34;&gt;HelDroid: Dissecting and Detecting Mobile Ransomware&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;em&gt;International Symposium on Research in Attacks, Intrusions and Defenses (RAID)&lt;/em&gt;.
  
  &lt;p&gt;








  



&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;/publication/andronio_heldroid_2015/andronio_heldroid_2015.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  PDF
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;button type=&#34;button&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary my-1 mr-1 btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/publication/andronio_heldroid_2015/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/button&gt;














&lt;/p&gt;

  
  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
